Guide to the Papers of Cecilia Razovsky (1886-1968), undated, 1913-1971
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, N.Y.
- Series I: Personal, undated, 1913, 1917-1946, 1951-1971; Boxes 1-2, and Oversized Folder.
  - Subseries 3: Written Works, undated, 1917, 1920, 1922, 1926, 1929-1940, 1955, 1962; Box 1, Folders 5-7, and Oversized Folder.
    The earliest published work in this subseries, located in Folder 5, is an article titled "The Season of Love," and was published in The Survey in 1917. Folder 5 also contains published versions of "These Families Want a Chance," and a review Razovsky wrote on a Maurice Kapf book. Razovsky's manuscripts include "Soviet Children Have Their Say About Books" and "Russian Children Learn to Read" an addition to and a translation of a pamphlet she found during her trip to the U.S.S.R. in 1931, and "A Wise and Virtuous Woman" reviewing Pearl Buck's autobiography My Several Worlds. Razovsky's notes on conditions for women in South American countries is of interest and is dated circa 1947. The final item in Folder 5 is an undated manuscript is titled "Locating Relatives" that was written for her family.
    Folders 6 and 7 contain published works by Razovsky. A full list is available in the item description.
    See also:
    Series I: Personal, Box 2, Folder 4, Item #14 "Forty Thousand New Brazilians;"
    Box 2, Folder 5 Item #2 and Item #3 "El Paso-The International City".
    Series II: National Council of Jewish Women; Box 2, Folder 8, Item #11 NBC Radio Broadcast by Razovsky
    Series III: NCC, Box 3, Folder 5, Item #2 "An Ounce of Prevention" and Item #3 "The Present Status of Jewish Settlement and Jewish Migration to Brazil and the Argentine."
    Series III: NCC, Box 3, Folder 7, Item #4, Item #9, and Item #10 memoirs of Razovsky's experience with S.S. St. Louis.
    Series IV: National Refugee Service, Box 5, Folder 1, Item #5 "How Does the Refugee Get Here?"
    Series VIII: United HIAS, Box 7, Folder 5 "Forty Thousand New Brazilians;" Box 7, Folder 7, Item #11 Speech address regarding Latin America; and Box 7, Folder 7, Item #22 draft "A Quarter Century of Brazil's Progress".
    - Miscellaneous Articles, undated, 1917, 1932, 1940, 1955, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "The Season of Love"., December 22, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        The Survey.
      - "These Families Want a Chance," unknown publication., circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        First hand cases of immigrants being affected by the quota law.
      - Statement by Razovsky on a visit she and her husband took in 1931 to the U.S.S.R., undated, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Visited during a famine, illiteracy was high, found in a bookstore a pamphlet on what Soviet children read.
      - "Soviet Children Have Their Say About Books", September 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "Karpf, Maurice J., Jewish Community Organization in the United States, New York 1939, [Book Review]," Jewish Social Studies, date stamped April 25, 1940., September 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Typewritten notes on conditions for women in South American countries., circa 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - "A Wise and Virtuous Woman.", January 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Book review of Pearl Buck's autobiography My Several Worlds.
      - "Russian Children Learn to Read," translated by Dr. Davidson, signed by Razovsky, 1962., undated, May and June 1931, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Attached is a list of children's books published by one publishing house for May and June 1931.
      - "Locating Relatives.", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Describes her case work with finding lost relatives. Written for her family; she writes of finding the relatives of Uncle Morris.
    - Published Works About Immigration., 1920, 1922, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Fragment, "? Pilgrims"., October 30, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Three Per Cent or At Ellis Island, A Play in Two Scenes. New York: General Committee of Immigrant Aid at Ellis Island., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Tragic story of immigrants being sent back because quotas are exhausted; social workers play major parts.
      - "The Operation of the Three Per Cent Law." Foreign-Born: A Bulletin of International Service., March 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "What is the Cable Act?", October 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Reprint from The Immigrant.
      - "America's Present Immigration Policy: The Visa and Quota Laws as they Affect the Clients of Social Agencies.", 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - "Adult Immigrant Education"., September 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        The Jewish Center. Also includes review of her book What Every Woman Should Know About Citizenship.
      - I-19, or The Council Lends a Hand, A One Act Sketch., October 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        From "Foreword": "Because of the new immigration law, many men in this country who are not yet American citizens are separated from their wives and children still living abroad. During the long period of separation, the husbands sometimes become indifferent and neglectful towards their families. The Department of Immigrant Aid of the National Council of Jewish Women has received many requests from agencies abroad to locate such husbands and induce them to send maintenance to their families until they may be reunited in this country. These cases are classified in the files of the office of the Department of Immigrant Aid as 'I-19' Domestic Relations cases."
      - What Every Woman Should Know About American Citizenship, New York: National Council for Jewish Women., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Cover page signed by her. Encouraging women to become citizens, learn to read and write, vote, be "good citizens." Picture in back of a NCJW English class, with woman in sheitl in front.
      - What Every Immigrant Must Know, NCJW., 1922 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Published Works About Immigration, 1929-1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (See also item in oversized folder)
      - "The Jew Re-Discovers America: Jewish Immigration to Latin American Countries," Jewish Social Service Quarterly., March 1929; 2 copies. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Oi, Mein Mann!," "a ten minute sketch describing social service at the piers.", November 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "Deportation of Alien Jews," The Jewish Social Service Quarterly., December 1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Handicaps in Naturalization: A Study of the Effects of High Fees Upon the Naturalization of Aliens in the United States., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        N.Y.: National Council on Naturalization and Citizenship.
      - "The Problem of the German Refugees," The Reform Advocate, December 7, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        [Item in Oversize Folder OS1]
      - "Immigration and the Alien in 1936 ," Better Times, June 1, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Manuscript of "The Stranger in Our Midst", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "The Stranger in Our Midst," Eve., February 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        "The National Council of Jewish Women represents a social service organization rather than a national minority group... It's [sic] activities for more than forty years have been inspired by an eagerness to make a contribution to American life. It was this zest which caused the National Council of Jewish Women to undertake a program of service to foreign born men and women who have come to these shores to live, - a service designed to incorporate them into the American way of life."
      - Making Americans, N.Y.: National Council of Jewish Women, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Inscribed on title page, "With love and kisses to my b.f. and s.c., Cel"
      - "How the Refugee Reaches This Country", December 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Social Work Today
  - Subseries 4: Later Years, 1951-1971; Box 2, Folders 1-6.
    Material is arranged by format and subject.
    This subseries documents Razovsky's "retirement" years, which were in many ways as busy as her professional life. Razovsky used her contacts in the United HIAS, NCJW, the American Friends of Hebrew University, and the American Council for Nationalities Service, particularly when she was planning a trip to South America, to solicit possible projects. Documented here are reports and letters from her trips to Brazil in 1954, 1958 and 1963, Argentina in 1963, and Mexico in 1959. Razovsky and Davidson were also busy changing their residences; they moved to Jackson, MS in 1948; Austin, TX in 1957; El Paso, TX in 1961; and San Diego, CA in 1964. In addition, the couple owned a house in Fire Island, N.Y. that they sold in 1962. In each community, Razovsky involved herself in local immigration matters and speaking events. Included are correspondence and programs for speaking engagements she held for the United Jewish Appeal in Jackson, MS (Folder 1); Temple Beth Israel in Austin, TX (Folder 1); Austin Chapter of Hadassah (Folder 1 and 3), and the Speakers Services for the United Nations in honor of World Refugee Year (Folder 3). Also mentioned is her work for Hungarian refugees in Texas (Folder 2); reports she wrote on the immigration situation in El Paso, Texas for Cuban refugees (Folder 4 and 5); and her work planning an immigrant service for Mexican-Americans in San Diego, CA (Folder 4). Of interest is the detailed method in which Razovsky completes a project when she helps the American Friends of the Hebrew University plan a fundraising dinner in honor of the Jewish Mayor of Dublin, Robert Briscoe (Folder 1).
    Razovsky's continued contacts with women involved in Liga Feminina in São Paulo, Brazil is apparent in letters she received from Luiza Klabin Lorch (Folders 1 and 2) and Susanna Frank (Folder 3). She recommended Brazilian women, one of whom was Susanna Franks, for two NCJW scholarships to bring them to the U.S. for training (Folder 2). Apparently Davidson was working on a book in 1960 about Brazil; it is unclear if his work was ever published. Razovsky also was occupied writing the manuscript "Forty Thousand Brazilians." A draft of her manuscript is included as well as her correspondence to James Rice, Executive Director of United HIAS Service and Alfred Hirschberg for their editorial comments (Folder 4). Folder 6 includes a diary of her trip to South America in 1963. Excerpts from her diary may have been used when writing her manuscript [see Box 7, Folder 5]. There are three immigration case studies Razovsky assisted with, concerning individuals from Brazil (Folders 2 and 4) and Romania (Folder 3).
    Additional items consist of a letter Razovsky wrote to Hon. Alberto Gonzales Fernandez, congratulating him on his appointment to the President of Columbia's cabinet (Folder 2); a memo from Israel Jacobson, United HIAS Service, writing of the urgent need for community studies for new immigrants (Folder 1); a letter to Reader's Digest enclosing an anecdote Razovsky remembered concerning Albert Einstein (Folder 4); and a form letter Razovsky wrote to her friends after her surgery in 1965.
    See also: Series VIII: United HIAS Service.
    - Correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Letter from Katherine A. Engel, National President of NCJW to Razovsky in Jackson, MS., February 27, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Invites Razovsky to become a member of the National Committee on Overseas Service.
      - Letter from Fred S. Weissman, Executive Secretary of Selfhelp of Emigres from Central Europe to Razovsky in Jackson, MS., November 23, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Razovsky sent them a check in memory of Clothilde Feibelmann.
      - Letter from Luiza Klabin Lorch in São Paulo, Brazil to Razovsky and Davidson., March 9, 1954 and November 10, 1954; 3 pages (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Responding to a letter Razovsky sent to her from Israel. Most of the three page letter is written in German, an addition dated November 10, 1954.
      - "To The Overseas Committee," signed by Razovsky, Jackson, MS., August 31, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        She is unable to attend their meeting and has little information concerning Brazil. Writes of her trip to Brazil; she met many of the women she had previously worked with in 1937 and 1946. She talks of the possibility of some of the women coming to the U.S. for orientation and training.
      - Letter from Jonah B. Wise, National Chairman of the United Jewish Appeal to Razovsky in Jackson, MS., May 31, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Thanking her for her address to the United Jewish Appeal Womens' Division luncheon.
      - Letter from Frederick R. Lachman, Executive Vice President of The American Friends of the Hebrew University to Razovsky in Austin, TX., January 20, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        He is very happy to hear she is willing to travel and do some work for them in Texas. Wishes to negotiate with her for her work.
      - Letter from Frederick Lachman to Razovsky in Austin, TX., February 5, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Lachman asks for her help with arranging a fund raising dinner in honor of the Jewish Mayor of Dublin, Ireland, Robert Briscoe.
      - Letter from Razovsky to Dr. Lachman., February 6, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Responds to a letter he wrote January 30th. She is able to work for him two or three days a week.
      - Letter from Razovsky to Al Goldstein, Executive Director, Jewish Community Council, Houston, Texas., February 8, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Asks him if he can assist with the fund raising dinner for Robert Briscoe.
      - Letter from Razovsky to Dr. Lachman., February 9, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Responds to his letter dated February 5th. Reports on the results of her efforts to find a city for his fund raising dinner.
      - "Report on Visit to Houston, Texas" by Razovsky., March 20, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Houston will be the city hosting the Briscoe fund raising dinner.
      - "Our Guest Speaker: Mrs. Celia Davidson. Theme: The Refugee is Always With Us.", April 26, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Program from Temple Beth Israel [Austin, TX], Sabbath Worship Services.
      - Memo from Israel G. Jacobson, United HIAS Service to Razovsky., December 19, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        He writes of the urgent need for their overseas offices and International Red Cross to obtain profiles of general and Jewish communities that immigrants can resettle into.
      - News clipping, unknown publication. "Hadassah to Hear Talk by Mrs. Morris Davidson.", undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Razovsky will speak on "Israel and the International Situation" at an Austin Chapter of Hadassah luncheon. Razovsky, a Hadassah member for 25 years, is currently a resident of Austin, TX.
    - Correspondence, April 1958-May 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Letter from H.S. to Razovsky in Brazil. H.S. was successful in finding a job for a woman Razovsky was helping., April 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Letter from Israel G. Jacobson, United HIAS Service in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil to Razovsky in Austin, TX., May 7, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        He sent the letter to Austin, since she mentioned she might be returning home in the first week of May. Writes of several HIAS matters.
      - Letter from Habli Adler (?) at Essex House in New York to Razovsky., June 18, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Thanking Mrs. and Dr. Davidson for their kind letter regarding the death of Mario.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Irving Engel, President of American Jewish Committee., July 11, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Engel and his colleagues are planning to visit South America. She just returned from spending a year in South America and writes of the overall importance of having closer contact with Jewish communities in South America.
      - Letter from Irving Engel to Razovsky in Fire Island, N.Y., July 16, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Thanks her for her letter and confirms the importance of his mission.
      - Letter from Razovsky to Hon. Alberto Gonzales Fernandez, Secretary General to the President, Bogota, Columbia., August 21, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Congratulates him on his appointment to the President's cabinet.
      - Letter from Razovsky to Hortense Goldstone, Head Department of Overseas Service, NCJW., October 5, 1958 and September 30, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Responds to Goldstone's letter of September 30th. Emphasizes that Brazil should receive "first consideration" for council scholarships. Razovsky recommends two women from Brazil.
      - Letter from Ann Rabinowitz, United HIAS Service to Razovsky, Fire Island, N.Y., October 13, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Regarding Maria Insarova who wishes to immigrate to the US from Brazil.
      - Letter from William Males, United HIAS Service to Razovsky, Fire Island, N.Y., October 20, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Regarding Maria Insarova's case.
      - Letter from Maria Insarova to Razovsky., October 28, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        She requires an affidavit to come to the U.S.
      - Letter from William Males to Razovsky, Austin, TX., November 17, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Regrets that United HIAS can be of no assistance in Insarova's case.
      - Copies of two work references for Mrs. Insarova., April 25, 1943 and November 8, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Letter from Hortense U. Goldstone, Head Department of Overseas Service NCJW to Razovsky in Austin, TX., November 3, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Thanks Razovsky for her recommendation, and informs her Mrs. Frank has been offered a fellowship. Mentions that the NCJW Austin Chapter has disbanded.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Morton Friedman, Personnel Officer, United HIAS Service. Thanking him for the reimbursement check for her expenses in returning to Austin., November 18, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Letter from Edward B. Marks, Executive Director of United States Committee for Refugees to Razovsky, Austin, TX., January 7, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Thanks her for her December 24th note, and will try to locate for her an article concerning Hungarian refugees in Texas.
      - Letter from Ruth Hutton Fred, Executive Director Jewish Family Service, Houston, TX to Razovsky in Austin, TX., January 8, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Writes concerning the Hungarian refugees. Attached is a copy of an article "Going Rough for Hungary Refugees."
      - Letter from James P. Rice, Executive Director United HIAS Service to Razovsky in Austin, TX., February 12, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        He writes they have no important role currently in regards to Roumanian immigration. HIAS is having a slower year and will not be adding personnel in the near future.
      - Letter from Luiza Klabin Lorch in São Paulo, Brazil to Razovsky and Davidson., May 26, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Gives a report on the Lorch family.
    - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Israel G. Jacobson, United HIAS Service in Rio de Janeiro., September 10, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        For his information, she will be speaking for the Speakers Services United Nations for World Refugee Year.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky in Austin, TX to Israel Jacobson., September 12, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        They returned three weeks ago to Austin, and includes their profile on Mexico. Razovsky plans to take courses at the University of Texas until January, when they will go to Venezuela (their first visit) for an Ophtalmology Conference.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Henry Friedman, United HIAS Service., September 19, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        She encloses a bill of her expenses incurred in Mexico City.
      - Flyer: "Hadassah Brings You a Special Treat! A Review of the Fascinating New Book "Ben Gurion" by Robert St. John, Reviewed by Dr. Morris Davidson," [Austin, TX]., November 14, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Letter from Chaim Lazdeiski Comite Central Israelita de Mexico to Dr. Davidson in Austin, TX., December 3, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Letter from Antonia Robinson, President of the International Council of Jewish Women in Canada to Razovsky in Austin, TX., December 19, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Thanking Razovsky for her offer of help in Venezuela.
      - Letter from Clara V. Friedman, United HIAS Service to Razovsky in Austin TX., September 4, 1959 and March 16, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Replying to her letter to Ann Rabinowitz concerning the Zoltan Strohli case. Attached are a series of letters dating from September 4, 1959 concerning the Strohli case. Mr. Strohli from Rumania wishes to obtain visas for him and his family to immigrate to Israel. Margarita Zimmerman, Strohli's Aunt living in Mexico, is concerned for him.
      - Letter from Israel G. Jacobson, United HIAS Service in Rio de Janeiro to Razovsky and Davidson in Austin, TX., May 27, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        A West coast regional office was recently opened. Additional general news.
      - Flyer: "Austin Committee for Refugees", May 29, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Razovsky is Secretary. Channel 7 will present a film "Call from the Stars." Appeals for help with admitting refugees to U.S.
      - Letter from Susanna Frank in Brazil to Razovsky and Davidson., September 20, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Writes of Razovsky's possibility of returning to Brazil, and recent Liga Feminina news.
      - Letter from Israel G. Jacobson to Razovsky, Fire Island, N.Y., November 8, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Morris Davidson has almost completed his book on Brazil, and additional generalities.
      - Letter from Leo, United HIAS Service in São Paulo, Brazil to Razovsky., November 12, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Speaks of recent HIAS Brazil news, as well as the high cost of living.
      - Letter from Antonia Robinson, President of the International Council of Jewish Women in Canada to Razovsky in New York, N.Y., December 7, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Thanks Razovsky for her offer of help on her upcoming visit to São Paulo, Brazil.
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Antonia Robinson., December 11, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Their principal reason for visiting Brazil is to help with Dr. Davidson's book. Includes a resume of her past activities in Brazil.
      - "Final Summary: From Pakistan to Paris," not signed., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Reports on women's conditions in Pakistan, Lebanon, Iran, Israel, and Athens, Greece.
    - Correspondence, undated, 1961-1965, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Copy of letter and report from Razovsky to Read Lewis, Executive Director of American Council for Nationalities Service., October 25, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Part one of two of her report on El Paso, Texas, concentrating on the international aspects and immigration situation there. [See Box 2, Folder 5, Items 2 and 3.]
      - Copy of letter from Razovsky to Shirley Bird, Program Supervisor, University of Texas., November 28, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Razovsky requests the University to schedule a one-day Institute on world refugee problems. Razovsky and her husband have just moved to El Paso, Texas. Attached is correspondence between Razovsky and Edward B. Marks, Executive Director of the United States Committee for Refugees, and correspondence from Otto W. Gobius, United National High Commissioner for Refugees and Shirley Bird, concerning scheduling a program. Razovsky writes that she is currently a volunteer for the Jewish Community Council in El Paso, managing their case work and writing for their monthly Bulletin.
      - Letter from Edward B. Marks, Executive Director of the United States Committee for Refugees to Razovsky and Davidson., January 10, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Outlines the programs for 1962.
      - Letter from Hanny Cohrsen, Assistant to Director of the American Council for Nationalities Service to Razovsky., February 20, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Wishes to know where to deliver her mail.